# **Amit Kumar Singh**

## Fullstack Developer \* DevOps

Ranchi, Jharkahnd (+91) 82100-98916 amitsin6h@gmail.com.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/amitsin6h/ https://github.com/amitsin6h

Self-taught computer programmer. Currently Founder, Fullstack Developer & DevOps in start-up Devconsole. I have 2.5+ years of experience specializing in backend/infrastructure, web development and security. I love to share my programming knowledge with the students. A super nerd who loves Linux and enjoys to customize all of the development environment. Interested in devising a better problem-solving method for challenging tasks, and learning new technologies and tools if the need arises.

## **Work Experience**

#### Founder, Fullstack Developer

Jan 2019 - Present

Feelin

## V2.1.0 - V3.0.0

- Updated the complete UI/UX of the app using React Native, and other third-party libraries
- Updated the backend using Apollo, Graphql, Express
- Designed the product website using MERN stack
- Implemented Redis caching technique
- Updated MongoDB schema for the product
- Built and deployed overall service infrastructure utilizing Docker containers.

#### V1.0.0 - 2.1.0

- Developed the complete UI/UX of the product using React Native and other third party libraries
- Designed the product website using HTML, CSS, and other javascript libraries.
- Implemented RESTful API server using Expressis and Nodeis
- Implemented API request validation using
- Implemented API caching technique to handle
- Implemented Flynn PaaS to manage product on
- Implemented Git for the project
- Designed advance schema for the complete product
- Built and deployed overall service infrastructure utilizing Docker container, Flynn PaaS( Opensource focusing on high-availability, fault tolerance, and auto-scaling

#### **Open Source Contributor**

Mar 2019 - May 2019

GirlScript Summer of Code

MEVN CLI: A CLI tool for getting started with the MEVN stack. It offers a super-simple boilerplate template and additional utilities for building a MEVN stack-based web app.

## **Education**

## MBA, IT & Systems

2019 - 2021

IMS, Ranchi University

 Selected for "Business English for Young Professional Workshop" conducted by U.S Embassy

## **BBA**, Marketing

2015 - 2018

Marwari College, Ranchi University

## AISSCE, Commerce

AISSE

2013 - 2015

2013

Central Academy, Bariatu

# Army Public School, Ranchi

 Completed 2 years (2010-2012) in Army wing 3JH BN NCC Ranchi as Lance Corporal/ Corporal. Also cleared 'A' Certificate examination held in 2012 under the authority of Ministry of Defence, Government of India

#### **Hackathons & Achievements**

- 2020, **eLife Innovation Leader**, eLife
- 2019, Intel Edge Al Scholar, Udacity
- 2019, Y Combinator Startup School
- 2018, OpenTechNights Winner, FOSSASIA
- 2017, Quality Assurance Contributor, Mozilla
- 2017, **First**, Hackathon De Corps
- 2016, **Second**, UTKRAANTI'16 with Padarth'16 IIT Bombay
- 2016, **Assocaate Trainer**, App Development Training for Nepalese
- 2015, **Top 10**, App Hackathon (Gov. of Jharkhand)

## Founder, Fullstack Developer

Ian 2018 - Nov 2018

Devconsole

- Developed the complete UI/UX of the product
- Designed the REST API server using Expressis and Nodeis
- Implemented API request validation using
- Designed MongoDB schema for the complete product
- Built and deployed overall service infrastructure utilizing Docker container, Flynn PaaS

#### Research Intern

Jun 2018 - Jul 2018

LinuxWorld Informatics Pvt Ltd

- SAAS(Software As A Service) A one-click implementation
  was achieved which provided the clients Firefox browser
  and VLC media player software's on their systems from
  DOCKERS running on the cloud server.
- STAAS(Storage As A Service)
  - Block Storage In Block storage we used ISCSI Protocol to provide clients with block storage available at the cloud to be used at the client system.
  - Object Storage In Object storage, using NFS and SSHFS Protocol to provide user fixed storage overcloud.
- CAAS(Container As A Service) A one-click launch, starting, stopping and removing and providing the terminal of docker container was achieved.
- **PAAS(Platform As A Service)** A one-click launch of python platform was provided for clients where they can code as they wish.
- **Hadoop** A CGI based web portal was developed for a one-click setup of hdfs and map-reduce cluster depending on the requirements of the client per se, the size of the cluster required, and the number of processors required for the big data analysis.
- Machine Learning The web service for the client was secured by Face recognition using machine learning and also include parts of speech recognition using python modules. IMAGE PROCESSING constitutes a large portion of the security aspect of the service.
- Ansible The entire configuration requirement of the project was met by the creation of ANSIBLE playbooks for both the client and the cloud.
- Dockers For the safe and secure single client-based service production, most of the services were provided through dockers only

#### Skills

- Front-End: HTML5, CSS3, JS, JQuery, Bootstrap, AngularJS, ReactJS, React Native, Redux, SocketIO
- Back-End: NodeJS, GraphQL, Apollo, Python, PHP, SocketIO
- Web Server: Nginx, Apache
- Mobile App: React-Native, Android Studio, Ionic,
- **Desktop App:** NW.js
- Database: NoSql, MySQL
- Web Framework: MERN Stack, MEAN Stack, Django, Flask, Codelgniter, LAMP
- Programming Languages: Python, JavaScript, PHP
- Version Control Tools: Git, Github, Bitbucket
- PaaS: CloudJiffy, Dokku, Flynn
- **DevOps:** Ansible, Splunk
- Big Data: Hadoop, Hive, Spark, Splunk
- Data Analysis: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plottly
- Others: Web Security, OWASP TOP 10, Networking, Web Scrapping, Linux, Quality Assurance, Data Mining

## Certifications

- 2019, cloudyBoss accreditation cBX82 Technology
- 2017, Red Hat Certified System Administrator
- 2017, Red Hat Certified Specialist in Ansible Automation
- 2016, Intro to Python for Data Science, DataCamp

## **Projects**

**Devconsole -** An online student and startup platform

**Al Monkey -** Al based web browser which consult user based on their search query

**MozCode Paste -** This project aims to paste code, share code and get the code reviewed. This project was shortlisted for Mozilla Pulse

**Air Notes -** Notes app in which notes can be synced online

**UC News Clone -** A clone of UC News app which shows news from diffrent news website.

**Django Twitter -** Twitter clone using python and django web framework

## **Digital Marketing Intern**

lan 2018 - Feb 2018

Genesis Digisec

- Developed complete SEO and Google analytics for a wordpress website, also worked in UI/UX of the website
- Suggested online marketing strategy for the promotion of the website

#### Jr. Researcher

Feb 2017 - Aug 2017

Cyber Peace Foundation

- Worked in Indian Honeynet Project
- Invloved some website and web application related projects
- Developed windows and Linux software using NodeWebkit

## Software Developer

Nov 2016 - Feb 2017

ResultsTrack Pvt. Ltd

- Involved in Data Visualization and Data Analysis projects, alon with some websites and web application projects
- Created an android app to collect survey in offline mode and automatically gets updated whenever the internet was connected

#### Intern

Aug 2016 - Nov 2016

Nathcorp Inc

• Involved in Data Visualization and Data Analysis projects and worked in dynamic graphs and maps using php and third party javascript library

#### Volunteer

#### **Code Contributor**

OpenGenus

 Code contribution for different algorithms in Cosmos. Suggested idea and worked on mockup of Cosmos Code Compiler (C3)

#### **Code Contributor**

PyCon India 2017

- Working with web development team for fixing the web related issues
- Volunteered for Machine Learning Fruitful and Fun using Orange talk

#### **Code Contributor**

PyConf Hyderabad 2017

 Working with web development team for code contribution to website and invloved in fixing web related issues in github

#### Club Leader

HackClub

 Responsible for building local community of developers in college and universities and organizing meet-ups

## Mozillian

Mozilla

- Responsible for event organizing, meet-ups for community and create FOSS Awareness in colleges, schools and universities
- Quality Assurance contributor from Mozilla India team